Okay, today's daf is דף קידושין נון, Daf Kiddushin Nun, 50, and
we pick up at the very bottom of מ"ט עמוד ב' Mem
Tet Amud Bet at a new משנה. Mishnah. על
מנת שאני כהן ונמצא לוי, al menat she'ani Kohen venimtsa Levi, so
a man marries a woman and says on the condition that I
am a כהן Kohen and he's discovered that he's a לוי, Levi,
לוי ונמצא כהן Levi venimtsa Kohen or the reverse, נתין ונמצא ממזר
Natin venimtsa Mamzer on the condition that I'm a נתין, Natin, which
is a Gibeonite, and it turns out, which is a lower status
of personal status, but he turns out that he's a ממזר Mamzer
and in all these cases, the first one mentioned of the pair
is the more higher status or the more preferred
one, or ממזר ונמצא נתין Mamzer venimtsa Natin he said it was
a ממזר, Mamzer, turned out to be a נתין, Natin, so whether
he said better and turned out to be worse, or worse and
turned out to be better, בן עיר ונמצא בן כרך Ben ir
venimtsa ben krach if he said he lived in a town and
it turned out that he lived in a city, or בן כרך
ונמצא בן עיר Ben krach venimtsa ben ir or a city and
it turned out he lived in a town. Now because as you'll
notice, the better one is mentioned first, the presumption of the משנה
Mishnah is that it's better off living in a town than in
a city. And if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says
בן עיר ונמצא בן כרך, ישיבת כרכים קשה, Ben ir venimtsa ben
krach, yeshivat krachim kasha, it's difficult living in a city, שהכרך הוא
מקום שווקים shehakrach hu mekom shevakim there's a lot of
markets, it's a noisy place, והיוקר מצוי vehayoker matsui the rents are
expensive, costs are high, ודוחק עוברי ושבים vedochak ovre veshavim it's very
crowded. Of course, exactly those things is why some people think it's
better to live in a city than in a town. So that's
interesting what it is implicitly reflecting about the attitude of the משנה.
Mishnah.
Okay, על מנת שיש לי בית קרוב למרחץ ונמצא רחוק al menat
sheyesh li bayit karov lemerchats venimtsa rachok on the condition that my
house is close to the bathhouse, that's nice to have
those easily accessible, those amenities, and it winds up that it's actually
distant, so it's worse than promised, or רחוק ונמצא קרוב rachok venimtsa
karov that it's distant and it turns out that it's close, על
מנת שיש לי בת או שפחה מגודלת al menat sheyesh li bat
o shifcha megudelet on the condition that I have a daughter or
a maidservant who is, we'll read this the simple פשט, pshat, which
is an adult, somebody who can help out around the house, although
if you remember earlier the גמרא Gemara had a different reading of
that, ואין לו ve'ein lo and it turns out he doesn't, על
מנת שאין לו ויש לו al menat she'ein lo veyesh lo he
says I don't have them and it turns out he does have
it, them, שאין לי בנים she'ein li banim on the condition I
don't have sons, that is a preferable status because that means that
there won't be other,
specifically sons here because there won't be other people competing for the
inheritance with the children of this woman, שאין
לו ויש לו she'ein lo veyesh lo it turns out he does
have, או על מנת שיש לו ואין לו o al menat sheyesh
lo ve'ein lo or he says on the condition that I have
and it turns out he doesn't, so that becomes better than promised,
none of those does it work. That's actually quite fascinating that the
משנה Mishnah doesn't even end by saying אינה מקודשת. eina mekudeshet. That's
somehow presumed because that was the ruling of the previous משנה. Mishnah.
So again, you'll remember in the previous משנה Mishnah there was a
debate that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said that if it was turned
out better than promised, that it would work, that somehow it's assumed
to be that the person would be okay if it was better
even though it was explicitly said על מנת, al menat, but רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon is not debating this משנה Mishnah because as the
גמרא Gemara said, issues of personal status actually maybe better isn't better,
maybe you don't want somebody of a higher status. Anyway, that's how
the גמרא Gemara explained it. But anyway, all these cases are whether
the condition turned out better than promised or worse than promised, she's
not מקודשת. mekudeshet. ובכולם uvechulam and here is the important additional line
that gets added, אף על פי שאמרה בלבי היה להתקדש לו af
al pi she'amra belibi haya lehitkadesh lo even if she says in
my heart I was already planning to marry the guy even with
I don't care כהן, Kohen, לוי, Levi, I love him, it didn't
matter, he said that, but I didn't care about that, אף על
פי כן אינה מקודשת. af al pi chen eina mekudeshet. She's still
not married. Once you make something on the condition of X, that
becomes the legally binding framing of the marriage. וכן היא שהטעתהו vechen
hi shehit'athu and the same way he is deceiving her, the same
would be true if she would deceive him, make something on the
condition and the condition would not wind up to be true. Again,
it's worth noting that the משנה Mishnah speaks about לטעו leta'u to
deceive, but really it's not about the deception per se, or the
גמרא Gemara never makes it about the deception, it's really that something
was made on the condition of something and the condition did not
turn out to be true. So the primary new idea of the
משנה Mishnah is even if she says I didn't care about that,
it doesn't matter. What's legally binding is what is said and that
leads to an extremely important principle,
articulation of a principle,
which comes right at this גמרא. Gemara. This גמרא Gemara is going
to be the core discussion of the principle of דברים שבלב אינם
דברים. devarim shebelev einam devarim. That things that are in the heart
are not legally binding, things have to be said in order to
have meaning within the legal system,
and that is a huge principle throughout ש"ס Shas and this is
the גמרא Gemara that discusses it. So let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. ההוא גברא דזבין לנכסיה אדעתא למיסק לארעא דישראל. Hahu
gavra dezavin lenichsei ada'ata lemisak le'Ara deYisrael.
A person sold off his property, רש"י Rashi emphasizes it's his... his
home, and his plan was to make עליה, aliyah, but he never
said anything to anybody. Okay. ובעידנא דזבין לא אמר ולא מידי, U-ve-idna
de-zavin lo amar velo midi,
when he sold it, he didn't say I'm doing it because I'm
planning on making עליה. aliyah. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, הוי דברים שבלב,
havei devarim she-ba-lev, and presumably then it didn't work out and he
didn't wind up going to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and now he's
homeless. So can he reverse the sale? So אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
says רבא, Rava, הוי דברים שבלב. havei devarim she-ba-lev. The idea that
it was on that condition, you know, that was the, that was
the reason why and somehow he only sold it because he was
assuming he was going to be able to do, to make עליה,
aliyah, that's all just things in his heart. They're, you know, they're
things that are unarticulated, ודברים שבלב אינם דברים. ve-devarim she-ba-lev einam devarim.
Things that are unarticulated have no halakhic weight and meaning. All right.
Now, מנא ליה לרבא הא? minalei le-Rava ha? Where does רבא Rava
get this idea? Obviously one possibility is our משנה, Mishnah, which is
why we're having that discussion now, but we're going to see about
the different possibilities and which ones really are, you know, most strongly
prove רבא's Rava principle. הא אילימא מהא דתנן Ha eileima me-ha de-tnan
from what we taught top of נ' עמוד א', nun amud aleph,
יקריב אותו. yakriv oto. The פסוק pasuk says in the beginning of
ויקרא Vayikra that if a person, you know, makes a... אם עולה
קרבנו מן הבקר im olah korbano min ha-bakar if a person, you
know, brings his קרבן korban an עולה, olah, it says יקריב אותו,
yakriv oto, he should bring it. And that's seen as an extra
phrase, okay, because it says, it already said זכר תמים יקריבנו, zachar
tamim yakrivenu, so why does it say יקריב אותו? yakriv oto? He
should bring it. מלמד שכופין אותו. Melamed she-kofin oto. You force him.
יקריב אותו, yakriv oto, you make him bring a קרבן korban if
he took a נדר. neder. יכול על כרחו? Yakhol al karko? Maybe
even if he, he resists? Like, so תלמוד לומר talmud lomar לרצונו.
lirtzono. It says it should be for his, you know, לרצונו, lirtzono,
you know, it should be, I know, for his, like on his
account, on his, you know, on his behalf. But the way it's
reading it here is a literal לרצונו, lirtzono, he has to desire
it. Now, how can you have both of those? He has to
want it and you force him to do it. הא כיצד? Ha
keitzad? How do you put those together? כופין אותו עד שיאמר רוצה
אני. Kofin oto ad she-yomar rotzeh ani. You force him until he
says fine, I want to do it. You're beating me up until
I say I want to do it, so I'll say I want
to do it. All right. Now, the גמרא Gemara points out, he
verbally says he wants to do it, but evidence makes it clear
that he doesn't want to do it.
So, so the גמרא Gemara says הא, so you see, אני and
אמאי, amai, רוצה אני, rotzeh ani, excuse me, ואמאי, הא Ve-amai ha
ליביה לא ניחא ליה? In his heart clearly he doesn't want to
do this, or at least there's a good reason that he doesn't
want to do it. אלא לאו Ella lav this proves
רבא's Rava principle, דאמר דברים שבלב אינם דברים. de-amar devarim she-ba-lev einam
devarim. Legally we go by what he says and not by what
he's thinking. And he says he wants to do it, so legally
that's what's binding, and that's considered to satisfy the demand that the
קרבן korban has to be brought לרצונו. lirtzono. And the גמרא Gemara
says one minute. ודילמא שאני התם דאנן סהדי דניחא ליה בכפרה. Ve-dilma
shani hatam de-anan sahadei de-nicha lei be-khaparah. Maybe there it's, we can
say that he really in the end does want to do it
because he wants to get an atonement, so even if it required
a little arm twisting, deep down when we finally got him to
realize what he really wants all along, and maybe, you know, דברים
שבלב devarim she-ba-lev is, you know, and maybe דברים שבלב, devarim she-ba-lev,
if we would know that that was what the person was thinking,
maybe that would be different. But here, you know, we can assume
he says he wants to, he wants to. All right, which gets
to the question, right, because there's two questions here. If you think
that what's going on in a person's heart, in a person's mind
matters, then the first step is you have to be able to
prove it. How do you know the person's telling the truth about
what they're saying? But the principle of דברים שבלב אינם דברים devarim
she-ba-lev einam devarim is not just saying we can't, we don't know
that that's really what the person was thinking. It's saying even if
somehow we find out it's what the person was thinking, it doesn't
matter, it's not legally binding. Okay, so here the גמרא Gemara says
how do you know, you know, maybe deep down he really does
want to, and that's why it works, and not because we discount
what he really is thinking. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says
אלא מסיפא. ella mi-seifa. Fine, the end of this, of this, of
this משנה. Mishnah. וכן אתה מוצא בגיטי נשים. Ve-khen ata motzei be-gitei
nashim. The same is true when it comes to a גט. get.
ושחרורי עבדים, Ve-shichrurei avadim, and freeing a slave. כופין אותו עד שיאמר
רוצה אני. Kofin oto ad she-yomar rotzeh ani. When there's a time
when בית דין beis din decides that a גט get must be
given or a freeing of a slave must happen, even if the
person resists, you force the person until they say they want to
do it. ואמאי? ve-amai, Why is this true? והא בליביה לא ניחא
ליה? Ve-ha be-libei lo nicha lei? He doesn't want to, and here
you can't say he wants to be atoned. He wants to stay
married to his wife. I mean this is the big problem with
עגונה agunah and where, you know, בית דין, beis din, you know,
that, you know, the, the fact that if a בית דין beis
din would choose to use force, it would work if they would
get him to say רוצה אני, rotzeh ani, something that can't happen
here in the States but can happen in Israel. But anyway, that's
a much larger question about, you know, why they are or are
not using force when they actually have the ability to do so.
But the principle is that if they get him to say רוצה
אני, rotzeh ani, you get him to say he wants to, it
doesn't matter what he's thinking. That seems to be an excellent proof
to רבא Rava of
דברים שבלב אינם דברים. devarim she-ba-lev einam devarim. ואמאי Ve-amai? הא לא
ניחא ליה אלא לאו משום דאמרינן דברים שבלב אינם דברים.
lo nicha lei ela lav mishum de-amrinan devarim
she-be-lev einam devarim. גמרא Gemara says no, ודילמא שאני התם משום דמצוה
לשמוע דברי חכמים. ve-dilma shani hasam mishum de-mitzvah lishmo'a divrei chachamim. Maybe
that's different. Maybe they are, you know, you can't say he wants
to be atoned like the sacrifice, but deep down, it's because the
בית דין beis din is forcing him, we'll say that deep in
his heart he wants to do the right thing, you know? Everybody,
the פינטעלע ייד. pintele yid. רמב"ם Rambam actually goes on this at
length, and the רמב"ם Rambam says, you know, that a person really
does want to do, you know, the right thing and what בית
דין beis din tells him, but his יצר הרע yetzer hara is
getting in the way. So we're helping give a little pushback against
the יצר הרע yetzer hara to let his יצר הטוב yetzer hatov
express itself. Very sort of optimistic view of human nature. And therefore
it's saying that the principle here might not be דברים שבלב אינם
דברים. devarim she-be-lev einam devarim. It might be that, you know, that
it could be that he really does want to do what he's
saying if the, if בית דין beis din is forcing him. In
the end of the day, people want to be part of their
religious community, and maybe they do want to do it, you know,
when they're pushed a little bit. Okay, it seems to be pretty
good proofs to רבא, Rava, but the גמרא's Gemara saying you can't
prove it in the end.
All right, אלא אמר רב יוסף, ella amar Rav Yosef, so רב
יוסף Rav Yosef says מהכא, me-hacha, from the following משנה. Mishna.
המקדש את האשה ואמר כסבור הייתי שהיא כהנת והרי היא לויה. ha-mekadesh
es ha-isha ve-amar kasavur hayisi she-hi kohenes ve-harei hi levaya. A man
marries a woman and says, oh, you know, I thought she was
the daughter of a כהן. kohen. It's interesting, calls her כהנת, kohenes,
not בת כהן. bas kohen. And it turns out that she's the
daughter of a לוי, Levi, a
לויה. levaya. לויה ונמצאת כהנת levaya ve-nimtzas kohenes עניה והרי היא עשירה
aniya ve-harei hi ashira עשירה והרי היא עניה, ashira ve-harei hi aniya,
or the reverse. מקודשת, mekudeshes, it is valid, מפני שלא הטעהו, mipnei
she-lo hit'ahu, because she did not deceive him. Again, notice the emphasis
again in the משנה Mishna of deception, and it seems to be
about the wrongness of deceiving, but again, you know, is that the
point or is the point that nothing was said? It was all
unarticulated. That really seems to be the focus that the גמרא's Gemara
consistently having, not about the aspect of deception. Okay, so even though
he says, well, I thought, that does not invalidate because it was,
it was not articulated. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואמאי הא קאמר
כסבור הייתי, ve-amai ha-ka-amar kasavur hayisi, but the גמרא, Gemara, okay, that
seems to be a great proof to רבא, Rava, right? Because that's
because, okay, so fine, nothing was articulated, but that was the assumption
he was working with. So why don't we go with what he
was
thinking? אלא משום דאמרינן דברים שבלב אינם דברים. ella mishum de-amrinan devarim
she-be-lev einam devarim. It must be because we say דברים שבלב אינם
דברים. devarim she-be-lev einam devarim. So אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye,
so that's a pretty good proof, right? And now, you know, again,
there always is a question about like how do you know he's
telling the truth and so on. But bracketing that, all right, here
he says, this is what I was thinking, and we completely don't
care about that. It's completely irrelevant that he claims he was thinking
this. So says אביי, Abaye, דילמא שאני התם דלחומרא. dilma shani hasam
de-lechumra. You're right, you've proved there that we discount it, but there
we're being מחמיר. machmir. We're saying that we're not going to take
what he said and treat her as an unmarried woman. Oh, well,
you said you thought she was a כהן, kohen, turned out to
be a לוי, Levi, all right, fine, she doesn't need a גט.
get. No, you know, we're not ready to, to go by that.
You know, we're not ready to, so it's true, we're going to
discount what you said you were thinking, but that's because we want
to play it safe. That doesn't mean we would discount it to
be מיקל. meikel. We might discount it to be מחמיר. machmir. So
if you really want to prove דברים שבלב אינם דברים, devarim she-be-lev
einam devarim, you have to give me a case where we discount
it even to the point of being lenient. So let's take a
look. אלא אמר אביי מהכא, ella amar Abaye me-hacha, אביי Abaye says,
I'll tell you where you get it from. בכולם אע"פ שאמרה בלבי
היה להתקדש לו אע"פ כן אינה מקודשת. bakulam af al pi she-amra
belibi hayah le-hiskadesh lo af al pi chen einah mekudeshes. Our משנה,
Mishna, our משנה, Mishna, she, you know, the guy said on the
condition that I'm a כהן, kohen, turned out he was a לוי,
Levi, and she says, I don't really, you know, after she accepted
the money and it turned out he was a לוי, Levi, she
said, you know, I really didn't care about that. And we said
it doesn't matter, you're not married. So we're being מיקל. meikel. We're
completely discounting her claim that she really didn't care and we're saying
the condition wasn't met, you're not married. So we're ignoring דברים שבלב
devarim she-be-lev for the sake of being מיקל. meikel. So that should
be a really good proof like רבא. Rava.
So, ואמאי, ve-amai, why is it true? הא קאמרה בלבי היה, ha-ka-amra
belibi hayah, I really didn't care, it was in my heart I
didn't care about this. ודילמא, ve-dilma, so גמרא Gemara says, no, ודילמא
שאני התם דכיון דאתני לאו כל
כמינה דעקרא ליה לתנאיה. ve-dilma shani hasam de-kivan de-asni lav kol kaminei
de-akei lei letna'ei.
Right? There you're right, you've proved דברים שבלב אינם דברים, devarim she-be-lev
einam devarim, but אינם דברים einam devarim to go against when you
explicitly articulated otherwise. So there, you know, since you stipulated, כיון דאתני,
kivan de-asni, you can't go ahead and say, oh, in my heart
I, my, that goes against what was explicitly stated. It was said
the קידושין kiddushin was taking place on the condition that he's a
כהן. kohen. You can't say, well, in my heart I was thinking
that that shouldn't matter, that that doesn't count. So you're right, you've
proved דברים שבלב אינם דברים devarim she-be-lev einam devarim to be strict,
you've proved דברים שבלב אינם דברים devarim she-be-lev einam devarim that we're
even going to be מיקל, meikel, but that's to not negate something
that was stated explicitly. Can you, that, let's go back. let's go
back to our case about selling on the condition that the guy
was planning on going, making עליה. Aliyah. Okay, nothing was stated explicitly.
He didn't say, "I'm selling despite any travel plans I might have."
So how do you know you would not take into account in
that case things that that person was thinking? Okay, so אלא אמר
רב חייא בר אבין עובדא הוה בי רב חסדא ורב חסדא בי
רב הונא.
Ella amar Rav Chiya
bar Avin uvda hava bei Rav Chisda veRav Chisda bei Rav Huna.
So this, you know, case came in the ישיבה Yeshiva of רב
חסדא Rav Chisda and רב חסדא Rav Chisda it was brought up
in the ישיבה Yeshiva of רב הונא. Rav Huna. ופשטוה מהא—they Upashtuha
me'ha were discussing this and they finally were able to find support
for רבא'ס Rava's statement from the
following: האומר לשלוחו הבא לי מן החלון—ah, Ha'omer lishlucho havi li min
hachalon the מעילה Me'ilah case. We had this before when we were
discussing the basis of שליחות. Shlichus. Somebody says to a שליח, Shaliach,
"Go ahead and bring me that money, you know, that's in there,
that's at the
windowsill," ומן הדלוסקמא—from Umin hadeluskema some type of like
of a box, והביא לו—and Vehevi lo he brings him. And then
it turns out and he goes ahead and he spends the money,
and it turns out that that was הקדש Hekdesh money. So the
בעל הבית Ba'al habayis מעל Ma'al because this is the principle of
שליחות Shlichus by מעילה. Me'ilah. The שליח Shaliach did what I said,
so even though it was a שליח Shaliach who did it, by
מעילה Me'ilah we have this principle of שליחות Shlichus and money of
הקדש Hekdesh was spent for חולין, Chullin, and therefore I have been
מועל. Mo'el. And here's the
kicker: אף על פי שאמר בעל הבית—I'm Af al pi she'amar ba'al
habayis sorry, I think I missed a line—והביא לו אף על פי
שאמר בעל הבית לא היה לי בלבי אלא על זה, Vehevi lo
af al pi she'amar ba'al habayis lo haya li belibi ella al
ze, even though the בעל הבית Ba'al habayis says, "No, no, no,
I didn't mean from like that half of the right side of
the windowsill, I meant from the left side of the
windowsill." Okay, כיון שהביא לו מזה בעל הבית מעל. Keivan shehevi lo
mize ba'al habayis ma'al. It doesn't matter, it doesn't matter that you
said you were thinking only of the money on that side and
he went on that side, at the end of the day he
did your שליחות. Shlichus. Now, why can't you say ואמאי הא קאמר
בלבי?
Ve'amai
ha ka'amar belibi? He said, "But no, I was intending otherwise." So
the שליחות Shlichus really was—he wasn't my שליח Shaliach when he took
from the right side, I was thinking the left side. All right,
so that's a case where the דברים שבלב Devarim shebelev are not
contradicting anything that was said and we are still completely discounting it.
You can't say לקולא Lekula or לחומרא Lechumra here because like either
the בעל הבית Ba'al habayis is going to have to bring the
קרבן Korban or the שליח, Shaliach, and we completely discount it and
it has no relevance להלכה, Le'halacha, and therefore the שליחות Shlichus was
fulfilled and we ignore what the guy was saying "I was thinking".
אלא לאו משום דאמרינן דברים שבלב אינם דברים. Ella lav mishum de'amrinan
devarim shebelev einam devarim. You see that that's the principle: דברים שבלב
אינם דברים. Devarim shebelev einam devarim. So the גמרא Gemara says now,
ודילמא שאני התם דלמיפטר נפשיה מקרבן קאתי? Vedilma shani hatam delimeiftar nafshia
mikorban ka'ati? Now we get back to the question of how do
we know the guy's telling the truth? Right, because to really prove
דברים שבלב אינם דברים Devarim shebelev einam devarim you have to prove
that even if we could—even if we know you're sincere and we
know it's true, it has no halachic meaning. Maybe sometimes we just
discount it because we don't believe you. So the גמרא Gemara says
maybe he's lying because he wants to get out of a קרבן.
Korban. We're discounting because we don't believe him, not because it has
no halachic meaning. So the גמרא Gemara says: No, הוה ליה למימר
מזיד הוה. Hava lei lemeimar mezid hava. So the גמרא Gemara says:
No, if he only wanted to get out of a קרבן, Korban,
he had other things he could have said. He could have said,
"I knew it was הקדש." Hekdesh. Okay, and that's—so clearly he has
no reason to lie. Now, the answer to that is obvious, like
why would he want to say he intentionally took from הקדש? Hekdesh?
The גמרא Gemara says: לא עביד איניש דמשוי נפשיה רשיעא. La avid
inish demashvi nafshia rashi'a. No, that
you can't say. There's no way he ever would have said that
he was מזיד Mezid if he had another option to get out
of a קרבן. Korban. He doesn't want himself to look like a
רשע Rasha that he was willingly that he intentionally misspent הקדש Hekdesh
money. So okay, fine, but here's how he could have gotten out
of it if he if he wanted to just get out of
a קרבן: Korban: הוה ליה למימר נזכרתי. Hava lei lemeimar nizkarti. He
could have said, "Oh, you know what, when the שליח Shaliach was
off going to the store, I remembered that it was הקדש Hekdesh
money." And that would have been enough to get him off of
the hook and he would have been totally, you know, faultless. I
like—I forgot at the time when I told the שליח Shaliach to
spend the money, then he was off to the store, before the
era of cellphones, I remembered, I had no way of recalling him.
So that could have gotten him off of a קרבן. Korban. All
right, דתניא—we Detanya learned on a ברייתא: Braisa:
נזכר בעל הבית ולא נזכר שליח—if Nizkar ba'al habayis velo nizkar shaliach
the בעל הבית Ba'al habayis remembers and the שליח Shaliach did not
realize it,
שליח מעל. Shaliach ma'al. So this is a perfect case, okay, because
here what have we done? It's a case where דברים שבלב Devarim
shebelev are discounted even though it's not going against anything he said—window,
the guy took from the window, דברים שבלב Devarim shebelev are just
saying "I meant this side of the window and not that," it's
not contradicting anything that was said. It's not about לקולא Lekula or
לחומרא Lechumra here, because like either the בעל הבית Ba'al habayis is
going to have to bring the קרבן Korban or the שליח. Shaliach.
And we completely discount it, even if we believe he's sincere, because
if all he was trying to do was get out of a
קרבן, Korban, he had other things he could have said. So even
if we are totally prepared to believe that he is sincere, it
has no halachic meaning: דברים שבלב אינם דברים. Devarim shebelev einam devarim.
So that is a really
important. Now, the problem with this is that there are a lot
of exceptions. There are times when we say דברים שבלב devarim she-balev
are דברים. devarim. So, what are some of those exceptions? One is
something that is called
דברים שבלב כל אדם. devarim she-balev kol adam. It's like even if
it's not articulated, it's just self-evident based on the circumstances. Okay, that
opens up a whole can of worms, but, you know, that would
be a type of a thing. So, if the guy never, you
know, let's say never said I'm selling this because I'm planning on
making עליה, aliyah, but he's say, you know, but he's, you know,
I don't know, he's like on the phone to his, you know,
to his, well maybe that's already speaking and saying things. But anyway,
if through his activities it's clear or through the context it's clear,
that's like a category called דברים שבלב כל אדם. devarim she-balev kol
adam. Okay, it's self-evident.
Other times when you also deal with issues about like if somebody
is being forced, like the earlier cases about רוצה, rotzeh, you know,
where we're twisting his arm, you know, is is somebody operating under
clear sense of being compelled, does that then give weight to דברים
שבלב? devarim she-balev? The גמרא Gemara before seemed to be not, but
there's some discussion that it does. How about when somebody
is whole principle in the beginning of נדרים Nedarim called ידיים yadayim
where a person, you know, says an elliptical statement, he doesn't finish
it. A נזיר nazir is walking in front of him and he
says I will be, and we understand him to mean I will
be a נזיר. nazir. So that's when it's not like he made
a full sentence and now we're trying to modify it based on
something he's thinking. We're using context clues and what he must be
thinking and so on to to finish his sentence for him. So
there's a lot of these types of cases about דברים שבלב, devarim
she-balev, you know, where where we are willing to consider it, but
certainly if it's something that like is not being compelled and, you
know, and there's no obvious evidence and he's just saying well this
is what I was thinking, then even if we believe him, you
can't use what you're saying you're thinking and nobody had access to,
you know, to go ahead and that halakhically cannot be meaningful. So
that's the basic principle of דברים שבלב אינם דברים. devarim she-balev einam
devarim. I should say
that
there are a very important position that emerges from רמב"ם Rambam and
תוספות רי"ד Tosafot Rid also says, which is that this is particularly
true in two-sided exchanges, meaning right, like where there's another side, you're
sell there's a seller and a buyer, a man is marrying a
woman, you know, there's, well, you know, what were the other cases?
I guess a case of a שליח shaliach where you're making somebody
your agent and they're going to be like responsible for what you
do and so on. But things that are more one-sided, like specifically
this comes out from רמב"ם, Rambam, if giving a gift and giving
a גט, get, giving a גט, get, the other side, you know,
is against a woman's will, so and giving a gift, okay, somebody
has to accept it, but still, other people can accept it for
them. It's not so much a transaction. In those cases, we're more
willing, at least according to רמב"ם Rambam and תוספות רי"ד, Tosafot Rid,
to look at דברים שבלב. devarim she-balev. Because maybe one of the
reasons we discount דברים שבלב devarim she-balev is a basic issue about
fairness, right? How can it be fair to the other side if
we have to start worrying about what you're thinking and not articulating?
So legally we have to completely like just rule that out. But
maybe things that are more all about one side doing it, maybe
there's sort of more of a preparedness to consider that. Alright, so
those are anyway various factors. As I said, others look at cases
not a question about one-sided or two-sided, but just how much is
it sort of self-evident from the circumstances. All right. Now the גמרא
Gemara continues. Let's take a look.
Okay. ההוא גברא דזבין לנכסיה אדעתא למיסק לארעא דישראל. hahu gavra de-zavin
le-nikhsei ada'ata le-misak le-ara de-Yisrael. A man sold his property on the
condition to go to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, just like the previous
one, except here, although the גמרא Gemara doesn't say it, the point
is the גמרא Gemara before said he didn't say anything. Here, the
assumption is that he did say. He said, I'm planning on going
to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay. סליק, salik, so he went up,
he tried to make עליה, aliyah, ולא אסתדר—no, ve-lo istadar ולא אסתדר?
ve-lo istadar? He couldn't find a place to live, he couldn't find
a good job, you know, tried to make עליה, aliyah, didn't make
it work, came back. ולא אסתדר ליה. ve-lo istadar lei. So what's
the story? Was the condition met? He said on the condition that
I'm going to make or I'm planning on making עליה aliyah and
that's why I'm selling it, so he did—I mean, or he didn't
say I'm planning to make. I'm planning to go up to go
to Israel. So he went to Israel, but he didn't wind up
settling there. So what did he mean? אמר רבא כל דסליק אדעתא
למידר הוא. amar Rava kol de-salik ada'ata le-meidar hu. Since he said
since he said he was doing it because he was planning on
going to Israel, he meant planning on going and settling in Israel.
והא לא אסתדר, ve-ha lo istadar, and he didn't manage to find
a place to live, so the condition wasn't met, you know, the
intent wasn't satisfied and therefore the sale goes back. ולא אסתדר ליה.
ve-lo istadar lei. איכא דאמרי, ika de-amri, some say, אדעתא למיסק והא
סליק. ada'ata le-misak ve-ha salik. The opposite answer רבא Rava gave. He
said he was going to go and he went. And now he
came back, but it doesn't matter, he went. Okay, lay. Okay,
so two ways of interpreting
what his intent was and whether the condition was satisfied. ההוא גברא
דזבין לנכסיה אדעתא למיסק לארץ ישראל. hahu gavra d'zavin l'nichsei ada'ata l'misak
l'Eretz Yisrael. Another case, guy sold his property, planned to go up
to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. לסוף לא סליק, lesof lo salik, in
the end he changed his mind, he didn't go. So does he
have a right to reverse the sale? So
אמר רב אשי amar Rav Ashi said, אי בעיא סליק, ibai salik,
who's stopping
him? Go! You can't reverse the sale,
you said you still have the option of going. So איכא דאמרי,
ika d'amri, some say, אי בעיא לא סליק? ibai lo salik? That
he said נו, nu, who's stopping him? Okay, why can't he, if
he wants, can't he go up? Sounds like the same point. So
the גמרא Gemara says, what's the difference? מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu? Each
one is, each of those approaches is basically saying if he wants
to he can go. איכא בינייהו דאית ליה אונסא באורחא. ika beinaihu
d'islei unsa be'orcha. The question is if something really is stopping
him. Let's say it's really difficult to travel now and that's why
he's not going. So according to the answer of נו, nu, what's
stopping him, there's an answer. I'll tell you what's stopping him, the
road conditions are terrible. Oh, okay, then he has a legitimate reason
not to go, the sale is nullified. But if the point is
נו nu so go, you said you were going to go, go.
That indicates that as long as it's at all possible then you
can't,
because you can still go, it's still at least somewhat possible, the
sale is not nullified. Now there's something very interesting about this case
which is,
since when does he have
to feel compelled to live up to this condition? Right, if I
say,
I'm selling you this plot of land on the condition that I
walk around the block, I can choose whether I want to walk
around the block or not walk around the block and to whether
to make the sale valid or not valid. So if he's deciding
not to go to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael then that should nullify
the sale. Why, what's the response נו nu who's stopping you, why
don't you go? So this actually gets to another question that is
asked by the ראשונים, Rishonim, which is that there's a whole discussion
about when you make, do an act based on a condition, a
תנאי, tnai, that you need to do משפטי תנאים, mishpetei tna'im, you
need to do things based on how the condition was made by
בני גד ובני ראובן. Bnei Gad uBnei Reuven. You have to double
the condition, this will work, this will sell if I make עליה
aliya and if I don't make עליה aliya then it shouldn't happen
and you have to say first the yes before the no. There's
all of these conditions. And here like none of that gets said,
it seems like just as long as you say oh I'm planning
on making
עליה, aliya, that's why I'm selling it. So they make a very
important distinction, תוספות, Tosafot, רמב"ן, Ramban, others, between when the תנאי tnai
is considered to be external to the basic intent. Like if I
say I'm selling you this, it'll take effect if I walk around
the block, not if I don't walk around the block, that's a
completely trivial thing. And that means I want to use some external
device to
either to make it conditional or to prevent it from taking place.
There it's totally under my decision whether I want to walk around
the block or not walk around the block, but if I want
to create that external device to override the sale I have to
satisfy a lot of technical requirements. When I say I'm selling you
my house because I'm planning on making עליה, aliya, this is not
some external thing that's negating the sale. The fundamental central to why
I am here at this table selling you the house, why we're
doing this, is because of these plans. That is central to my
דעת da'at and central to my intent. When that's the case then
it's a fundamental question of did you really want to do it
and therefore you don't need any of these formal משפטי תנאים. mishpetei
tna'im. On the other hand, we can say look, you sold because
you were planning on making עליה, aliya, as long as that's still
a possibility, right, it's not some formal thing oh I'm not making
it, sale בטל batel give it back to me. Right? Your דעת
da'at was to do it and
there is nothing there that legitimately says that what you, your intent
and your plan, it was not working out according to what you
had assumed because all those assumptions are still in play, it's still
possible for you to make עליה aliya now it's just you deciding
not to do it. So a lot of very really important principles
here. Number one, דברים שבלב אינם דברים, devarim she-balev einam devarim, even
if we trust that that's what you mean, it's completely not halachically
relevant.
At the same time there are times where we do look at
דברים שבלב, devarim she-balev, if it's דברים שבלב כל אדם, devarim she-balev
kol adam, it's self-evident, if maybe
it's giving a context to understand what your words mean, maybe if
there's obvious force that's being exerted. Maybe דברים שבלב devarim she-balev matter
more in one-directional rather than two-directional transactions. Oh that's דברים שבלב. devarim
she-balev. And then there's a separate point which is even when things
are articulated, do they have to satisfy these formal rules. of conditions
and there there's a major difference whether the condition is seen as
external to the fundamental דעת daas or whether we're really not talking
about a condition as much as what's central to the דעת daas
of doing the transaction. So this is a major ש''ס סוגיא Shas
Sugya as you might have guessed. Let's take a look now at
the next משנה. Mishna. האומר לשלוחו צא וקדש לי אשה פלונית במקום
פלוני והלך וקידשה במקום אחר. Haomer lishlucho tze vekadesh li isha plonis
bemakom ploni vehalach vekideshah bemakom acher. So this you will remember, we
discussed this מראה מקום הוא לו. mareh makom hu lo. A man
who says to his שליח shaliach go and marry me this woman
in a certain place and he went and finds her in a
different place, אינה מקודשת eina mekudeshes she's not married because the שליחות
shlichus was only for that place. That's a principle of מקפיד, makpid,
not a principle of מראה מקום. mareh makom. There's a תנא Tanna
who argues by this about גט, get, doesn't appear here by קידושין.
Kiddushin. This our משנה Mishna assumes, if you say it, the שליחות
shlichus only works in that place. הרי
היא במקום פלוני וקידשה במקום אחר. Harei hi bemakom ploni vekideshah bemakom
acher. Now if he doesn't say go marry her in that place,
he says go marry that woman,
she's in such and such a place, and then it winds up
she's somewhere else, הרי זו מקודשת harei zu mekudeshes it does work
because that was not articulated in the context of the act of
which he is being empowered and which he's being made an agent,
there it just clearly a מראה מקום mareh makom in that scenario.
Okay, ותנן נמי גבי גיטין, u'snan nami gabei Gittin, we taught similarly
by a גט. get. האומר תנו גט לאשתי במקום פלוני ונתנו לה
במקום אחר. Haomer tnu get l'ishti bemakom ploni unesanu lah bemakom acher.
Somebody says give this גט get to my wife in such place
and she winds up being in a different place, פסול pasul it's
invalid. הרי היא במקום פלוני ונתנו לה במקום אחר כשר. Harei hi
bemakom ploni venesanu lah bemakom acher kasher. By the way she's in
such and such a
place and given in a different place, כשר kasher it's good. And
again that's by the way where the תנא Tanna disagrees. There's a
תנא Tanna who disagrees and says no even in the first case
he's just מראה מקום. mareh makom. But this assumes no if it's
said as part of the שליחות shlichus it is a technical part
of the שליחות. shlichus. וצריכא, Utzricha, and משנה Mishna has to teach
you this both by גט get and by קידושין. Kiddushin. דישמעינן גבי
קידושין, De'ishmieinan gabei Kiddushin, if it said by קידושין Kiddushin במקום במקום
bemakom bemakom like go marry her for me in this place, דלקורבה
קאתי dekureva ka'asi he's trying to bring her close, he's trying to
marry her, בהאי אתרא רחמו לי ולא ממלו מילי עלוי. behai asra
rachmu li velo mamlu mili aluy. So he's מקפיד, makpid, we can
assume when he says in that place he means that really cares
that it's in that place because in that
place people if you go and you go to this section of
town or whatever it is, people there know me and they'll say
nice things about me, certainly they won't say bad things about me,
it'll be a good place to marry her on my behalf. בהאי
אתרא Behai asra if you go in a different place, סנו לי
sanu li you'll find people that hate me, ממלו מילי עלוי mamlu
mili aluy and they'll say all nasty things about me and she'll
say no. So I really want you to be careful that you're
marrying her in a place where nobody comes and tries to שטער
דעם שידוך shter dem shidduch as they say.
אבל גבי גיטין, Aval gabei Gittin, but I would have thought that
maybe when it comes to a גט, get, דלרחוקה קאתי delerichuka ka'asi
that the guy is trying to push her away, אימא לא אכפת
ליה eima lo ikphas leh what does he care where it's happening?
She doesn't have a say, nobody's going to stop it, what does
he care what place it is? So maybe when he says this
place even that's always
מראה מקום. mareh makom. גמרא Gemara says ואי אשמעינן גבי גירושין, ve'i
ashmieinan gabei geirushin, okay but then just tell me by גירושין geirushin
that even there it matters and certainly by קידושין. Kiddushin. No, I
had a reason to think that maybe by a גט get he
more cares what place it is. Why? בהאי אתרא ניחא ליה דניבזי
Behai asra nicha leh denivzi because in this place I can tolerate
that I'm
a little bit of a disgrace.
Now רש''י Rashi says because it is a, if you look at
רש''י, Rashi, דליבזי שמגרשת אשתו גנאי הוא לו. delivzi shemegareshes ishto g'nai
hu lo. A man who divorces his wife it's a disgrace for
him. What's a disgrace? Disgrace that the marriage didn't work out,
disgrace that he married a woman that wasn't right for him, that
he's going to wind up being divorced, it's not exactly clear, but
it's a fascinating social commentary that the act of divorcing his wife
will be seen as disgrace for him. So maybe I want you
to do it in a certain place where I can more
tolerate this embarrassing thing is happening. It's fascinating the whole focus on
the man and him tolerating the embarrassment and how he's feeling as
a result of this whole process. בהאי אתרא לא ניחא ליה Behai
asra lo nicha leh and but in another place I
really much more care, I don't want it to be heard and
I'm very sensitive to that. אבל גבי קידושין אימא לא אכפת ליה
aval gabei Kiddushin eima lo ikphas leh but by קידושין Kiddushin what
do I care what place it takes place? וצריכא Utzricha so you
had to tell me both scenarios. Okay, that is the principle of
the question about מראה מקום mareh makom and our משנה Mishna assumes
that when it's articulated as part of the שליחות shlichus we always
assume that's part of the שליחות shlichus and not מראה מקום. mareh
makom. Next משנה. Mishna. המקדש את האשה על מנת שאין עליה נדרים
ונמצאו עליה נדרים. Hamekadesh es ha'isha al mnas she'ein aleha nedarim venimtzu
aleha nedarim. If a man marries a woman on the condition, now
she's the one making conditions on her, that she does not have
any vows that she has taken upon herself and it turns out
she did, אינה מקודשת eina mekudeshes then she's not married. כנסה סתם
ונמצאו עליה נדרים. Kensah stam venimtzu aleha nedarim. If he married her
and then it turns out that she has נדרים. nedarim. Now this
means by the way like even if he made the תנאי *tnai*,
he made the תנאי *tnai* on the condition you don't have נדרים
*nedarim*. It was not found out at the time of קידושין kiddushin
*kidushin*, then they had the נישואין *nisuin* and you know they had
sex and they got married and they went took it to the
next stage and they fully were living together, and then it turns
out that the נדרים *nedarim* are found. In that case, תצא בלא
כתובה kesubah *teitzei belo kesuvah* because the it was against the condition
he stipulated she can be divorced without a כתובה kesubah *kesuvah*, but
she still without you know so she doesn't get alimony as it
would be, but she still needs a גט *get*. Why does she
still need a גט *get*? Because this is based on the principle
of the concern of like אין אדם עושה בעילתו בעילת זנות *ein
adam oseh beilaso beilas zenus* that we assume that a man does
not want it to be that his act of sex winds up
being like not in the context of marriage. So even though he
made a תנאי *tnai*
there's an assumption that or at least we recognize that it's possible
that when they actually then had the נישואין *nisuin* and started living
together and had sex and so on, he basically felt like he
was מבטל *mivatel* the תנאי *tnai*. So because of that possibility we
assume that now they are really considered to be מקודשת *mekudeshes*, okay,
and but and still a גט *get* is needed, but divorced without
a כתובה *kesuvah*. This by the way raises the whole issue nowadays
of one of the solutions of the עגונה *agunah* is to make
a תנאי בקידושין *tnai bekidushin*, to make a תנאי *tnai* in the
קידושין kiddushin *kidushin* that if it turns out they're separated and they
don't get a גט *get* etc. retroactively they were never married. Do
we say that once they started living together that that automatically constitutes
a ביטול *bittul* of the תנאי *tnai*? Or is there a way
that you could be explicit and say even if we start marrying
you know living together the תנאי *tnai* is not going to be
בטל *battel*. Okay so this משנה mishnah *mishna* anyway that's what we
have here. כנסה סתם ונמצאו לה נדרים תצא בלא כתובה *Kinasa stam
venimtzu la nedarim teitzei belo kesuvah*. על מנת שאין לה מומים ונמצאו
בה מומים *al menas she'ein lah mumim venimtzu bah mumim* similarly says
on the condition that there's no physical blemishes and then it turns
out that there were before the נישואין *nisuin*, אינה מקודשת *eina mekudeshes*,
the marriage is void. כנסה סתם ונמצאו בה מומים *kinasa stam venimtzu
bah mumim* if they got had the נישואין *nisuin* and then saw
these blemishes תצא בלא כתובה *teitzei belo kesuvah* she still needs a
גט *get* but she doesn't get her כתובה *kesuvah*. שכל המומים הפוסלים
בכהנים פוסלים בנשים *shekol hamumim haposlim bakohanim poslim banashim* all the blemishes
that invalid are in you know invalidate כהנים *kohanim* invalidate women, which
is quite a fascinating statement because sometimes the מומים *mumim*, you know,
how like you know when presumably he says on the condition there
are no מומים *mumim* anyway, you know, more about this later. Let's
take a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does not get deal
with that line at all just deals very quickly with the first
part of the משנה mishnah? *mishna*. ותנן נמי גבי כתובות כהאי גוונא
*usnan nami gabi kesubos kehai gavna* the exact same משנה mishnah *mishna*
appears in כתובות *Kesubos* because this משנה mishnah *mishna* both talks about
the about the fact that the קידושין kiddushin. *kidushin* is not is
no good and that after the נישואין *nisuin* she's divorced without a
כתובה *kesuvah*. So it has relevance for כתובה *kesuvah* and relevance for
קידושין kiddushin. *kidushin*. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says הכא קידושין kiddushin,
איצטריך ליה *hacha kidushin itztrikh lei* so here the part of the
משנה mishnah *mishna* that was relevant was the קידושין kiddushin *kidushin* part
that that negates the קידושין kiddushin. *kidushin*, תנא כתובות אטו קידושין kiddushin,
*tana kesubos atu kidushin* once we're teaching the קידושין kiddushin. *kidushin* part
we teach what happens if they went through with the marriage and
had the נישואין *nisuin* and then the relevance for כתובה *kesuvah*. התם
*hasam* by in כתובות *Kesubos*, כתובות איצטריך ליה *kesubos itztrikh lei* we
wanted to talk about the relevance for כתובה *kesuvah* ותנא קידושין kiddushin.
אטו כתובות *ve'tana kidushin atu kesubos* so the first half was schlepped
along because of to get to the second part. Okay. המקדש שתי
נשים בשווה פרוטה prutah, *hamekadesh shtei nashim beshaveh perutah* אישה אחת בפחות
משווה פרוטה pachas mishaveh prutah, *isha achas bepachas mishaveh perutah* if a
man marries two women with a פרוטה prutah, *perutah* or one woman
with less than a פרוטה prutah, *perutah* so obviously none of this
works, אף על פי ששלח סבלונות savlanos אחר כך *af al pi
sheshalach savlonos achar kach* even if he sent סבלונות savlanos, *savlonos*, סבלונות
savlanos *savlonos* were traditional gifts that would be sent from the חתן
*choson* to the bride's family after the קידושין kiddushin. *kidushin*, okay, so
now the question is do we are we concerned that these סבלונות
savlanos *savlonos* are effect קידושין kiddushin, *kidushin* because the קידושין kiddushin *kidushin*
itself didn't effect it, אינם מקודשות *einam mekudashos* she's not married, שמחמת
קידושין kiddushin. הראשונים שלח *shemachmas kidushin harishonim shalakh* because it was just
doing it based on the first קידושין kiddushin. *kidushin*, this is not
intended to be a second קידושין kiddushin. *kidushin*, וכן קטן katan. שקידש
*vechen katan shekidesh* also if a boy under בר מצווה *bar mitzvah*
did קידושין kiddushin, *kidushin* and then after he became an adult he
sent these סבלונות savlanos. *savlonos* she is still she is not מקודשת
*mekudeshes*. Now what is the הוה אמינא *hava amina* that the סבלונות
savlanos, *savlonos* would make us reassess? There's one of two possibilities and
this ambiguity is going to be in the גמרא *Gemara* we're about
to see. One possibility which רש"י Rashi *Rashi* emphasizes is maybe these
gifts constitute new כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin? *kesef kidushin*. And what the
משנה mishnah *mishna* is saying is like no when he's sending these
gifts he's sending them because he thinks he's already married and we
should not assume that these these gifts are because exactly because he
just think he's married and not intended to be new כסף קידושין
kesef kiddushin, *kesef kidushin* and therefore she remains אינה מקודשת *eina mekudeshes*.
The other possibility, that's probably a very good פשט *pshat* in the
משנה mishnah *mishna*. The other possibility to consider which we'll see in
the גמרא *Gemara* is should we think that maybe because he's sending
these סבלונות savlanos *savlonos* he did another act of קידושין kiddushin *kidushin*
that was valid? Okay since סבלונות savlanos *savlonos* follow קידושין kiddushin *kidushin*
maybe some other act of קידושין kiddushin. *kidushin* that was valid occurred
that we don't know about. And the answer is like no we're
assuming these are based on. And the answer is like, no, we're
assuming these are based on the first act, we're not going to
guess that there was some new act that took place. Okay, so
the סבלונות savlanos are not considered to be evidence of some new
act of קידושין kiddushin, and they're not new money of קידושין kiddushin
because it's all based on his first invalid קידושין. kiddushin Okay, so
now the גמרא says like this: וצריכא, u'tzricha, you need both cases
about, or all three cases, about two women with a פרוטה, prutah
a woman with less than a פרוטה, prutah, and a קטן. katan
דאי אשמעינן שוה פרוטה, de'i ashmi'enan shaveh prutah, if it had just
told us the case of two women with a פרוטה, prutah. אידי
דקנפיק ממונא מיניה טעי, idei deka'nafik mamona minei ta'i,
since in the end he's giving a full פרוטה, prutah he might
think that even though it's only a half פרוטה prutah, per woman,
he might think it actually did work. Okay, and since he thinks
that it, that it did work, clearly the סבלונות savlanos are not
new קידושין. kiddushin אבל פחות משוה פרוטה, aval pachas mishaveh prutah,
but when he sends, gives a woman less than a פרוטה, prutah,
אימא ידעה דאין קידושין תופסין בפחות משוה
פרוטה, eima yada'at de'ein kiddushin tofsin bepachas mishaveh prutah, I might, like
presumably he knows that that's not valid קידושין, kiddushin it was less
than a פרוטה. prutah, וכי קמשדר סבלונות אדעתא דקידושין קמשדר, vechi kamshadar
savlanos ada'ata dekiddushin kamshadar,
and when he's sending these סבלונות, savlanos, he is sending them that
they should be a new קידושין kiddushin. because he obviously knew that
his earlier one wasn't good. But we don't say that. Even in
that case, we don't say that. ואי אשמעינן הני תרתי, ve'i ashmi'enan
hani tarti, if it had just said these two, the פרוטה between
two women or less than a פרוטה, הני תרתי משום דבין פרוטה
לפחות משוה פרוטה לא קים להו לאינשי, hani tarti mishum debein prutah
lepachas mishaveh prutah lo kim lehu le'inshei,
because you know, in one case you gave a full פרוטה, in
the other case if, I mean if it was actual cash presumably
you would know, but if it was an object that was worth
a little less than a פרוטה, maybe he didn't really know. So
in all those cases he assumed it was good and the סבלונות
savlanos is not going to be new קידושין. kiddushin אבל קטן שקידש,
aval katan shekiddesh, but if he was a minor, but if he
was a קטן who did קידושין, kiddushin, הכל יודעים שאין קידושי קטן
כלום, hakol yodim she'ein kiddushei katan klum, everybody knows that's not valid.
So in that case at least we should assume that the סבלונות
savlanos, were meant as a new קידושין. kiddushin, אימא כי קמשדר סבלונות
אדעתא דקידושין
קמשדר, eima ki kamshadar savlanos ada'ata dekiddushin kamshadar, maybe that case we
should assume that it's new קידושין. kiddushin קמשמע לן kamashma lan
that we don't say that, that we're not concerned with that without
any evidence. We just say it's all in the context of earlier
קידושין. Not everybody knows the הלכה, halacha,
there's no evidence that this is any קידושין, there's no evidence that
another קידושין took place, so it's nothing to worry about. That's what
our משנה says. Fine. Now we're going to see a debate of
אמוראים Amoraim whether you do worry about סבלונות. savlanos? Let's take a
look. איתמר. itmar. רב הונא אמר חוששין לסבלונות. Rav Huna amar chosheshin
lesavlanos.
When somebody sends סבלונות, savlanos we are concerned of קידושין. וכן אמר
רבה חוששין לסבלונות. vechen amar Rabbah chosheshin lesavlanos.
We are concerned with it. Now, here's a major debate of ראשונים
Rishonim what I mentioned before. Does this mean when we see that
somebody sent סבלונות savlanos, to a woman like a woman's family, that
means that we're concerned he intends it to be כסף קידושין? That's
what רש"י Rashi says. A lot of ראשונים Rishonim push back and
say, I don't understand, for something to be כסף קידושין, besides that
there have to be עדים, edim, okay, maybe there were עדים edim
and they're no longer around, but you know you have to explicitly
articulate הרי את מקודשת לי, harei at mekudeshet li, you have to
make it very clear that it's being done for the sake of
קידושין. רש"י says, well, maybe there was an engagement beforehand, but ראשונים
Rishonim really resist all of a sudden because of סבלונות savlanos we're
going to think that סבלונות savlanos, are themselves קידושין. They say, and
this is a simpler read in certainly for pieces of the גמרא,
that the question is if somebody sends סבלונות savlanos which are traditional
to be sent after קידושין, we're concerned that some קידושין took place
earlier that we don't know about. Okay, so רב הונא Rav Huna
and רבה Rabbah both say if there are סבלונות, sivlonos we'll go
with that read, if we see סבלונות being sent, we're concerned that
some קידושין took place earlier. אמר רבה ומותבינן אשמעתין, amar Rabbah umotvinan
ashmeitin, I asked on my own position, you know, this is my
position, I am concerned about קידושין. What do I do with our
משנה? אף על פי ששלח סבלונות לאחר מכאן אינה מקודשת. af al
pi sheshalach savlanos le'achar mikan einah mekudeshet. Like
our משנה says that we're not concerned with סבלונות, why am I
saying we should be concerned with סבלונות? אמר ליה אביי, amar lei
Abaye, רבה's Rabbah student, התם כדיקתני טעמא, hatam kideiktani ta'ama, you shouldn't
feel that that's a challenge to your position. The משנה makes it
clear why that case is not a concern: שמחמת קידושין ראשונים שלח.
she'machmat kiddushin rishonim shelach.
In that case, right, there was invalid קידושין, so we
assume that the סבלונות are linked to the invalid קידושין and nothing
to worry about. But you, רבה, Rabbah, are saying if all we
know about is a guy sends סבלונות, nothing else, in that case
we'll be concerned that there was a valid קידושין that took place
that we don't know about. So having an invalid קידושין neutralizes the
concern of the סבלונות after. But if you just have סבלונות, that's
your concern that maybe there's a קידושין we don't know about. איכא
דאמרי, ika de'amrei, some say, אמר רבה מנא אמינא לה, amar Rabbah
mana amina lah,
רבה Rabbah didn't see our משנה initially as a problem, he right
away saw our משנה as proof to his position. How do I
know my position? כדיקתני טעמא, kideiktani ta'ama, our משנה says שמחמת קידושין
ראשונים שלח. she'machmat kiddushin rishonim shelach. Okay,
that the reason סבלונות are not a problem is because they're explained
on the basis of the invalid earlier קידושין. הכא הוא דטעי. hacha
hu detai.
In our משנה *Mishna* he thinks that the first קידושין *kiddushin* was
good and that's what the סבלונות *savlanos* are about. הא בעלמא הוי
קידושין *Ha be-alma havei kiddushin*, normally though, if סבלונות *savlanos* are being
sent, we would assume that there is some קידושין *kiddushin* that they
represent that came before them. Again, רש"י *Rashi* would say we assume
that they were given for the sake of קידושין *kiddushin*. But we'll
go with the other read. Okay? So when I see סבלונות *savlanos*
being sent, if I don't know about anything that preceded, I'm going
to be concerned that there was some קידושין *kiddushin*. Okay, אביי לא
מיבעיא קאמר *Abaye lo mibaiya kamar*. And אביי *Abaye* would push back
and say no, it goes without saying. לא מיבעיא בעלמא דלא נחית
לתורת קידושין כלל *Lo mibaiya be-alma delo nakhis latoras kiddushin klal*, it
goes without saying that in a normal case
that somebody just sent סבלונות *savlanos* and you don't even hear of
any possible possibility of קידושין *kiddushin*, there's nothing to be concerned about.
Maybe he decided to send סבלונות *savlanos* before he was trying to
woo the woman or something. We'll see later that in some places
they send סבלונות *savlanos* before. So if there's no mention of קידושין
*kiddushin*, of course we're not concerned. אלא אפילו הכא דנחית לתורת קידושין
*Ella afilu hakha denakhis latoras kiddushin*, our משנה *Mishna* is telling you
even when there was a קידושין *kiddushin* that took place beforehand and
then you might think that the... you see he's trying to do
קידושין *kiddushin* and then there were סבלונות *savlanos*, maybe that makes you
concerned that he fixed his problem and did a good קידושין *kiddushin*
afterwards. אימא הוי קידושין *Eima havei kiddushin*, maybe it would be good.
קא משמע לן Kamashma lan, *Kamashmalan* that we're not concerned. Okay, so
you have this debate. When somebody sends סבלונות *savlanos* without anything preceding
or without us knowing that anything preceded, are we concerned that קידושין
*kiddushin* came before? מאי הווי עלה *Mai havye ala*, what was the
conclusion of all of this? אמר רב פפא באתרא דמקדשי והדר מסבלי
*Amar Rav Pappa be-asra demikadshi vehadar mesavli*, now there's major debates of
the ראשונים *Rishonim* about what the גירסא *girsa* is here, we're just
going to read with the גירסא *girsa* we have. In a place
where קידושין *kiddushin* comes first and afterwards סבלונות *savlanos* are sent and
then we see סבלונות *savlanos* being sent, חיישינן chashinan *khashinan*, we're afraid
some קידושין *kiddushin* must have taken place and maybe that we don't
know about. מסבלי והדר מקדשי *Mesavli vehadar mikadshi*, if it's a place
where they send the סבלונות *savlanos* before the קידושין *kiddushin*, לא חיישינן
*lo khashinan*, obviously there's nothing to be concerned about. Now, the גמרא
*Gemara* unpacks this. מקדשי והדר מסבלי פשיטא *Mikadshi vehadar mesavli peshita*, if
קידושין *kiddushin* comes before סבלונות *savlanos* and we saw סבלונות *savlanos*, obviously
we've got to be concerned that some קידושין *kiddushin* took place. לא
צריכא *Lo tsrikha*, you need it for the case דרובא מקדשי והדר
מסבלי *de-rubba mikadshi vehadar mesavli*, it's true, most people do קידושין *kiddushin*
before סבלונות *savlanos*, so that explains why you're concerned. ומיעוטא מסבלי והדר
מקדשי *U-miuta mesavli vehadar mikadshi*, and some do סבלונות *savlanos* first. מהו
דתימא ניחוש למיעוטא *Mahu detaima nekhush le-miuta*, I might think let's be
concerned for the minority. Now, ניחוש *nekhush* here with our גירסא *girsa*
means let's be concerned to be מחמיר *machmir*, but let's assume this
person fits into the minority. I mean, it makes a lot of
sense. Even if only twenty percent send סבלונות *savlanos* first, this person
sent סבלונות *savlanos*, we don't know of any קידושין *kiddushin*, all of
a sudden we should be concerned that there was קידושין *kiddushin* if
we don't know about it? There's a known twenty percent of the
population that sends סבלונות *savlanos* before קידושין *kiddushin*. So I might have
thought let's say he's part of that population. So קא משמע לן
*kamashmalan* that we don't say that because of the strictness of אשת
איש eshes ish. *eshas ish*, we're concerned enough about the fact that
there's סבלונות *savlanos* that there might have been a קידושין *kiddushin* that
took place beforehand since that's at least the way the majority of
the population act. Okay, בעי מיניה רב אחא בר רב הונא מרבא
*bo'i minei Rav Akha bar Rav Huna me-Rava*. רב אחא בר רב
הונא *Rav Akha bar Rav Huna* asked from רבא *Rava*. הוחזק שטר
כתובה בשוק מהו *Hukhzak shtar kesubah bashuk mahu*? Let's say that it's
known that this woman had a כתובה *kesubah* written up for her.
Does that mean that we are concerned that the קידושין *kiddushin* took
place? Or maybe the כתובה *kesubah* is given at the נישואין *nissuin*
or whatever, right? So if the woman is known that there was
a כתובה *kesubah* written up, maybe we should assume that the קידושין
*kiddushin* already took place, similar type of a question. So אמר ליה
וכי מפני שמחזיק שטר כתובה בשוק נחזיק בה כאשת איש *amar lei
vekhi mipnei she-makhzik shtar kesubah bashuk nakhzik ba ke-eshas ish*? So he
said what, I don't get it, like why should we assume just
because a כתובה *kesubah* was written up that she's already married? Like
maybe this is
something that maybe he was doing it in preparation for it, but
all of a sudden we should assume the קידושין *kiddushin* already took
place? מאי הווי עלה *Mai havye ala*, what was the conclusion? אמר
רב אשי *Amar Rav Ashi*, again it's going to depend on the
practice of the case. באתרא דמקדשי והדר כתבי כתובה *Be-asra demikadshi vehadar
kisvi kesubah*, in a place where the writing of the כתובה *kesubah*,
remember, it wasn't even given yet, but קידושין *kiddushin* would always occur
before the writing of the כתובה *kesubah*, חיישינן *khashinan*, then we heard
a כתובה *kesubah* was written, we have to be concerned that the
קידושין *kiddushin* took place. כתבי והדר מקדשי *Kasvi vehadar mikadshi*, if they
write כתובה *kesubah* before קידושין *kiddushin*, לא חיישינן *lo khashinan*, we're not
concerned. And again, the גמרא *Gemara* says מקדשי והדר כתבי פשיטא *mikadshi
vehadar kasvi peshiti*? If קידושין *kiddushin* always comes before it's written and
now it's written, obviously we need to be concerned there was קידושין
*kiddushin*? לא צריכא דלא שכיח ספרא *Lo tsrikha delo shakhiakh safra*. No,
you need it in a scenario where it's hard to find a
ספרא *safra*. Okay, so yes, the practice is you write it after
קידושין *kiddushin*, but also, it's not so easy to find a סופר
sofer *sofer*. מהו דתימא ספרא היא דאיתרמי, very reasonable thing. I'm thinking
about getting married. I haven't done the קידושין yet, but the סופר
is in town and he's not going to be in town for
another three months. So I get him to write up the כתובה
ahead of time. קא משמע לן, so that teaches us that no,
that even though yes, that is a possible scenario, just like before,
it's possible I'm sending סבלונות before the קידושין, people do that, but
since the standard is that the כתובה is only written after קידושין,
therefore that is enough of a reason to be concerned that a
קידושין already took
place and because of the weight of אשת איש. Of course, חיישינן
and then we go ahead and we try to figure it out,
but at least we start with that concern.